A Guide to the Prince William and Loudon County Family Papers, 1725-1970
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Prince William and Loudon County Family Papers 1725-1970
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10771
This collection contains ca. 1200 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the library from Beverley S. Thomas of Culpeper, Virginia on July 11, 1988.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of over 40 families primarily from Loudoun and Prince William Counties contains ca. 1200 items (4 Hollinger boxes, 1.75 linear feet) and consists of original material, such as financial and legal papers, personal correspondence, photographs and printed material as well as non-original genealogical notes.
The Alrich, Beans, Berkeley, Blackwell-Hunton-Smith, Gaskins, Heineken-Peters, and McIntyre families together contain a large portion of the primary material in the collection. Other family files contain mostly genealogical research but may have some original material.
Letters, school records, photographs and printed material concerning Bethel Military Academy in Faquier County can be found in this collection. There are two folders devoted to Bethel Military Academy which contain much of the information on the academy, but more may be found in the Blackwell-Hunton-Smith and McIntyre Family folders, which contain information pertaining to the two owners of the school, Major Albert Galatin Smith and Major R.A. McIntyre. Major Smith founded the school in 1867 and retained ownership until his death in 1892. He left the school to his son-in-law, Major McIntyre, who kept it until it closed in 1910. Major McIntyre was a member of the faculty of the academy from 1886 until 1899. For more information on the history of the academy, see University of Virginia masters thesis number 1353.
This collection also contains a group of letters (1800-1807) of Harriot Harrison written from her home, "A Soldier's Repose". They are in the form of an original copy book and a much clearer typewritten transcript. Due to the size of the copy book, the folder is filed as the last folder in Box 4.
Much of the genealogical research included in the collection is the work of either the Rev. Melvin Lee Steadman or Mrs. Walter Jewell.
The material found in each family's file is listed after their name. Financial and legal papers include deeds, wills, receipts, lawsuits, plats and business correspondence. Personal correspondence are letters written by or sent to the family. The category of genealogical notes includes family trees, inquiries from other researchers and brief family histories. Photographs, although often unidentified, have been kept in their original folder. Finally, printed material includes news clippings, announcements, invitations, programs and bulletins.
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically by family name, preserving the original order.
Contents List
- Adams Family 1957-1961, n.d. (Box 1)
  Genealogical Notes
  Photographs
  Printed Material
- Alrich Family 1851-1963, n.d. (Box 1)
  Personal Correspondence
- Armistead Family ca. 1952 (Box 1)
- Ashford Family 1846-1861, n.d. (Box 1)
- Ball Family 1944-1974 (Box 1)
- Ball-Elgin Family 1961-1963 (Box 1)
- Beans Family 1785-1965 (Box 1)
  Financial / Legal Papers
- Beatty Family 1847-1855 (Box 1)
- Bennett Family 1789-1790 (Box 1)
- Benton Family 1867-1883 (Box 1)
- Berkeley Family 1748-1977 (Box 1)
- Bethel Military Academy 1870-1963, n.d. (Box 2)
- Beveridge Family 1822-1832 (Box 2)
- Blackburn Family 1725-1784, 1970 (Box 2)
- Blackwell, Hunton, Smith Family 1787-1906 (Box 1)
- Blake Family n.d. (Box 2)
- Brunk Family 1891 (Box 2)
- Carrington-Ambler Family 1796-1823, 1954 (Box 2)
- Church Family n.d. (Box 2)
- Fairfax-Loudon Co. Line 1954-1955, n.d. (Box 2)
- Fischer Family 1851-1877, n.d. (Box 2)
- Fuller Family 1961 (Box 2)
- Gaines Family n.d. (Box 2)
- Gallagher Family 1849 (Box 2)
- Gantt (Gant) Family 1969-1970 (Box 2)
- Gaver Family n.d. (Box 2)
- Gilmour Family n.d. (Box 2)
- Gaskins Family 1821-1926, n.d. (Box 3)
- Gore Family 1957-1964 (Box 3)
- Green Family 1824 (Box 3)
- Griffith Family 1973-1974 (Box 3)
- Grimes Family 1960-1963 (Box 3)
- Grubb Family 1953-1972 (Box 3)
- Gulick Family 1956-1961 (Box 3)
- Gunnell Family 1786-1981 (Box 3)
- Hague Family 1951-1953 (Box 3)
- Hampton Family 1956 (Box 3)
- Harrison Family 1800-1963 (Box 4)
- Head Family 1954, n.d. (Box 3)
- Heineken-Peters Family 1870-1962, n.d. (Box 3)
- Hixson Family n.d. (Box 4)
- Lindsey Family 1967-1977, n.d. (Box 4)
- Ludlow Family 1856-1940 (Box 4)
- McIntyre Family 1882-1936, n.d. (Box 4)
- Minor Family 1897 (Box 4)
- Montgomery Family n.d. (Box 4)
- Moore Family n.d. (Box 4)
- Nelson Family n.d. (Box 4)
- Parker Family n.d. (Box 4)
- Scott Family n.d. (Box 4)
- Smith Family 1868-1927, n.d. (Box 4)
- Wren Family (18--) - 1970 (Box 4)